<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon vpon part of the second chapter of the first epistle of S. Iohn: Preached by Thomas Ingmethorp. The summe whereof is briefly comprised in this hexameter  ...</title>
            <author>Ingmethorpe, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 69 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14086</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106261</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841979</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841979</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6602</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04028)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6602)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 639:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon vpon part of the second chapter of the first epistle of S. Iohn: Preached by Thomas Ingmethorp. The summe whereof is briefly comprised in this hexameter  ...</title>
                  <author>Ingmethorpe, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes, printer to the Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1598.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6602:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON VPON PART OF THE SE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond chapter of the firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of S. Iohn: <hi>Preached by</hi> THOMAS INGMETHORP.</p>
            <p>The ſumme whereof is briefly compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this Hexameter:</p>
            <q>Omne tulit punctum qui <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> miſcuit arti:</q>
            <q>
               <l>He beares the bell awaie,</l>
               <l>that liues, as he doth ſafe.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iohn. 13.17.</bibl>
               <p>If yee knowe theſe thinges, bleſſed are ye, if yee doe them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>At Oxford, printed by IOSEPH BARNES, Printer to the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie. 1598.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6602:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6602:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVL, MASTER THOMAS FLIT, one of the head-magiſtrates of the Citie of Worceſter T. I. wiſheth increaſe of all thinges ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining both to this life and to the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, being impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned by diverſe, for the publiſhing of this Sermon, which (as they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted) not without ſome fruite they had hearde mee preach: I haue condeſcended at length vnto their deſire. The rather, for that by dedicating the ſame vnto your worſhip, I might be occaſioned (as I thought,) to giue-forth ſome teſtimony of my good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will
<pb facs="tcp:6602:3"/>and thankefulnes towardes you, to whom I am ſo deepely beholding, &amp; ſo many waies indebted. If there were no other thing but this, that at the Fonte you vouch-ſafed to vndertake for me, I ſhould over-ſhoote my ſelfe far, if I did not thinke very dutifully of you; but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ever ſince, you haue enameld, as it were, &amp; embroidered that graund-benefite with infinite other kindneſſes, from time to time, as occaſion was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred: Surely, if I ſhould not lay holde of every opportunity, whereby I might reflect any toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an affectionate minde I were highly to blame; yea my own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience would appeach and vpbraid me of foule ingratitude. Such therefore as it is: I do here offer &amp; preſent vnto you. Deſiring you to eſteeme of it, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſimple workema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip which hath beene mine: but according to the worth &amp; value of the ſtuffe, which hath bin all, I dare aſſure you, digged-out of the moſt precious mine of Gods word. My truſt is, the goodnes of the one, will
<pb facs="tcp:6602:3"/>bee alwaies able to counter-peiſe the rudenes of the other. God bleſſe you, &amp; preſerue you: that you may long liue, to be a principall ſtay &amp; ornament, to that worthy Citie, my natiue neſt. Where how ſore you will be miſſed, whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to tranſlate you from it vnto himſelfe, wee may take a ſcantling (no diſparagement to any) by the exceeding greate ſteede you long haue and daily doe ſtand it in. And thus recommending this homely preſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your good acceptation, and you and yours to the moſt gracious tuition and patronage of the Almighty, I take my leaue. From Stainton in the ſtreete, in the Biſhopricke of Durrham the 1. of <hi>March.</hi> 1597.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your VVorſhips in the Lord, <hi>THOMAS INGMETHORP.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6602:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6602:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere haſt thou (gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Reader) this ſimple Sermon of mine, made at the firſt for the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of few, but nowe by request ſet-forth to the common view. For my part,<note place="margin">Novi quàm ſit mihi c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſupellex.</note> truely I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meant it: but when frindes be ſet-on a thing, they are importunate, and wil not be ſaide nay. Indeede it would better fitte my note-booke, then the preſſe: yet if it ſhall pleaſe thee to giue it the reading, I doubt neither of thy profiting by it, nor of thy well accepting of it. It is no ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious pamphlet to raiſe mutinie, nor ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous toye to nouriſh wantonneſse; which the more thou peruſeſt, the more thou abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt thy time, and the more they affect, the the more they infect thee: but a ſounde and ſerious diſcourſe of holy Scripture; wherein is ſounded as with a ſhrill trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet a retraite from ſinne, and men put in
<pb facs="tcp:6602:5"/>minde, to ioyne vertue and truth, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and practice, repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and faith, a Godly life and a good beleefe together: vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon which two pointes, as vppon two poles, the whole ſkie of Christianitye is turned. God giue thee grace to followe the whole ſome cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell therein delivered, to his glory and thy comfort, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6602:5"/>
            <head>It is written in the ſecond chapter of the firſt epiſtle of S. Iohn the third, fourth, ſift and ſixt verſes.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>3. Hereby we are ſure that we knowe him, if we keepe his commandements.</q>
               <q>4. He that ſaith I knowe him, and keepeth not his commandements, is a lyer, and the truth is not in him.</q>
               <q>5. But he that keepeth his worde, in him is the loue of God perfect indeede: hereby wee knowe that wee are in him.</q>
               <q>6. He that ſaith he remaineth in him, ought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo to walke, as he hath walked.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Scripture (wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved in the Lorde) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of two partes: of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and a confirmation. The propoſition in effect im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth thus much, that the knowledge and faith of Chriſt, if it bee of the right ſtampe indeede, is never ſolitary, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies accompanied with the keeping of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements, whereby, as a tree by the fruit it is diſcerned: being conteined in theſe words: <hi>Hereby wee are ſure that wee knowe him, if wee keepe his commaundementes. He that ſaith, I knowe him, and keepeth not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6602:6"/>his commandements, is a lier, and the trueth is not in him.</hi> The confirmation ſtandeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> two reaſons: the one drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the effectes, wher it is ſaid, <hi>But he that keepeth his word, in him is the loue of God perfect indeede: Hereby we knowe that we are in him;</hi> The other derived fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the example of Chriſt in the clauſe following: <hi>He that faith her remaineth in him, ought even ſo to walke as hee hath walked.</hi> The ſcope and drift of all, is to beare downe the vanitie of thoſe men, which profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the name of Chriſt, lived not with ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vnchriſtianly, to the manifeſt flaunder and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation of the ſame. Wherein as in a glaſſe or mirrour, by waie of reflection, we may behold the ſpots of our owne deformity: whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation being compared with our profeſſion, is for the moſt part no more conſona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t therevnto, then the harſh iars of diſcord, to the ſweet har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of muſique, as if they had made a wager, which ſhould varie moſt either fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the vniting of which diviſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath bin made, ſo often, ſo earneſtly, both heere and elſewhere, that it may ſeeme, but a needeles or booteles office, to ſolicite the ſame agame. Howbeit, as the Phiſition never ceaſeth to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, till his ſicke pacie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be wholy recovered: even ſo it behoveth vs the Lordes Phiſitions, daily to applie the moſt wholeſome medicine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6602:6"/>of Gods word, till the maladie of ſin, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with mens ſoules are ſore diſeaſed, be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly healed and recured. But before I come to the particular points, let vs praie &amp;c.</p>
            <q>3. <hi>Hereby we are ſure that we knowe him, if wee keepe his commandements.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>4. <hi>He that ſaith, I knowe him, and keepeth not his commandements, is a her, and the trueth is not in him.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>This is the propoſition (as I ſaide) &amp; is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (if ye marke) of an excellent Antitheſis. A figure of ſpeech, very familiar with S. John, both in his Goſpel and Epiſtles, not ſo much for perſpicuitie, as vehemencie ſake. <hi>Hereby we are ſure that we know him,</hi> that is, by this argument, wee may certainely perſwade our ſelues, that we haue the true knowledg &amp; faith of Chriſt, if we keepe his commandementes. For the Apoſtle ſpeaketh not heere of a bart hiſtorical knowledge,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.19.</note> which the Divels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues haue, and are never the neerer: but of that ſaving knowledge, whereby we are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as the Prophet Eſay witneſſeth.<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.11.</note> But this be amplyfieth, by ſetting againſt it, another propoſition of the contrarie: <hi>Hee that ſaith I knowe him, and keepeth not his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, is a lier, &amp; the trueth is not in him:</hi> as if hee had ſaid, the keeping of Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements is an evident token of the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6602:7"/>and faith of Chriſt, to boaſt therefore of the one, without having apparent teſtimony of the other, is but a Thraſonicall brag, a lowde lie voide of trueth. Which accordeth with the premiſſes on this maner, whereas I ſaide be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that Chriſt was given vs of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>to be the reconciliation for the ſins of the whole world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.2.</note> and that we muſt vſe him for our <hi>mediatour and advocate with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> let no man gather therevpon,<note place="margin">verſ. 1.</note> that it is ſufficient to be called a Chriſtian, to learne the ſtories of the Bible by rote, neither yet to bee partaker of the holy Sacraments inſtituted by Chriſt. For beſides all this there is an other matter of far greater moment and importance required at our handes, namely, a liuely know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Ieſus Chriſt, which is a worke &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the holy Ghoſt. It graffeth vs who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into Chriſt: raviſheth vs with admiration &amp; loue of him, ſo as we hunger and thirſt after nothing more, then to teſtifie the ſame to the worlde, by our obedience towards him in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his commandements. This carefulneſſe to walke in the waie of Gods commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, who ſo feeleth effectualy wrought in him, may well aſcertaine his conſcience, to the vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ioy and iubily of his ſoule, that he is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the true knowledge and faith of Chriſt indeede. But otherwiſe, if he find no inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6602:7"/>no diſpoſition at all, but rather a backewarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and repugnancie in himſelfe that waie, let him leaue glorying in any ſuch vaine paradiſe: for he doth but he, &amp; plaie the Hypocrite. And this, as neere a I can vtter, is the true pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and meaning of the Apoſtles wordes. Wherein are wrapped many very good points of doctrine worth the vnfolding, as well for comfort as inſtrucion.</p>
            <p>And firſt it is not lightly to be paſſed over, that S. Iohn ſaith not barely, we think, or we ſuppoſe, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>by this wee are ſure, that wee knowe him.</hi> A cleare evidence, and ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g proofe, that we may haue certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſalvation. For ſalvation being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by faith, as the whole tenor of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture every where defineth, in that the Apoſtle heere plainely confeſſeth, wee may bee ſure of our faith, nay ſetteth downe an infallible note of the certaintie thereof, it cannot be, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhould be vncertaine or doubtfull of their ſalvation. This doth flatly repeale that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and wicked Cannon of the counſaile of Trent,<note place="margin">Seſſ. 6. c. 9.</note> whereby men are taught alwaies to ſtagger, and ſtand in doubt of their ſalvation, as being impoſſible for any in this life, to know of a ſurety that he in particular ſhall be ſaved, without by ſome ſpecial priviledge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, he be made privie therevnto. A faithles doctrine
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:6602:8"/>like a ſhippe in a ſtorme without helme or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe betwixt the billowes &amp; ſurges of the ſea? but no marvaile, though the Papiſtes do thus leſſon their ſchollers alwaies to doubt of their ſalvation, the ground, the matter and forme as it were, of whoſe doctrine, is their owne lucre and gaine. For once let this trueth be admitted off, that Chriſtians be by the worde and ſpirite of Chriſt aſſured of their ſalvation by him: then may they ſtreight, poore men, bid adue, &amp; ſinge a perpetuall <hi>requie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> for the ſoule of their prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, their pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, their trentals, their dirgies their chauntries, their cenſing, their ſinging, their ringinge, their maſſes and praiers for the dead, with whatſoever mercenary trumperie els of like ſtampe. For bar them of their profit (the onely butte, the onely white they aime at) and all theſe, I warrant you, will quickly lie in the duſt (if that common proverb be not wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly fathered on them: no pennie no <hi>pater noſter.</hi>) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in that they looke to bee ſaved by their owne workes, which (alas) they cannot but ſee in their giltie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces (howſoever they hood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winke &amp; blindfold their eys againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth) to be ſpotted &amp; vnpetfect, &amp; ſuch as ar not able to abide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> touch of Gods iuſtice: how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d reſolute me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but needs muſt remaine ſcrupulous and ſuſpicious of ſalvation, as not knowing, whether they haue deſartes enough
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6602:8"/>to ſerue their turne or no? Thus doth the ſpirit of giddines, wherewith the malignant Church is intoxicate and governed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Like the Rat:</hi> prodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeipſe S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rez</note> bewraie it ſelfe eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his owne doctrine.</p>
            <p>Secondly commeth to be marked the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine marke, wherby to diſcerne the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, from the counterfeit &amp; Hypocrite. True it is that faith maketh a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: howbeit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth many times lie hid, and we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not readily iudge of other mens mindes, wherein faith hath her ſeat and manſion: therefore the Apoſtle ſheweth, how the faithfull may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcried by an outward marke: &amp; that is the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Gods commandements. Whereby is meant, not that perfect and continuall abiding in all thinges commended and commanded in the lawe, to which condition,<note place="margin">Levit. 18.5.</note> 
               <hi>doe this and liue</hi> is annexed, (a burthen to heavie for any wordly wight to beare ſo long as we are invironed on every ſide with the infirmities of the fleſh:)<note place="margin">Gal. 3.12.</note> but only that careful ſtudie &amp; indevour, wherewith the faithfull ſoule is inflamed and ſet one fire towardes the commandements of God to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill them in ſome good meaſure, as God ſhall enable him, whereunto nevertheles, by reaſon of the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our nature, much imperfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will cleaue, will he, nill hee, when hee hath done the beſt he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Neither did S. Iohn faine this marke of his owne head, but learned it of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6602:9"/>his maſter Chriſt.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.23.</note> For he ſaith: <hi>hee that hath my wordes, and keepeth them, is he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth me:</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> And againe as it were doubling his blowe; <hi>he that loveth me not, keepeth not my word:</hi> &amp; in another where: <hi>ye are my frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds if ye doe whatſoever I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand you.</hi> So whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God the father had made ſolemne proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from heaven:<note place="margin">Mat. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>this is my beloved ſonne in whome I am well pleaſed:</hi> to admoniſh vs of our dutie withall, hee adioyneth: <hi>heare him:</hi> ſignifying thereby, not the hearing of thoſe thinges, which Chriſt ſhould giue in charge in his word with our outward eares only, but the expreſſing &amp; practiſing of the ſame in our liues and converſation: for they onely are pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced bleſſed of him,<note place="margin">Luc. 11.28</note> which <hi>heare the worde of God and keepe it.</hi> As therefore that ſon doth degenerate &amp; is not worthy to beare the name of his father, which ſtudieth not by all meanes poſſible to obey &amp; pleaſe his father: even ſo no more is he to be eſteemed a true Chriſtian, and child of God, which endevoureth not, as much as in him lieth, to approoue himſelfe to God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, by keeping of Chriſts commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, wherin only he delighteth. But aboue all, this one thing I would haue eſcecially noted, as it were w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a hand in the marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: that S. Iohn rec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>koneth for true &amp; faithful Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, only ſuch, as obſerue <hi>&amp; keepe the commaundements
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6602:9"/>of Chriſt.</hi> This toucheth to the quicke al thoſe that imagine Chriſtianity to be placed in the obſerving of humane traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: nay ſtifly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with tooth &amp; naile not ſome peece, but the very perfecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; as it were quinteſſence therof to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt therin. As for example; the Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Friet muſt no remedy be reputed holier the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reſt, becauſe he followes the rule of S. Francis. The Dominican, he preferreth himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Franciſcan, and all other Chriſtians: for that he profeſſeth the rule of S. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nike: &amp; ſo of the reſt of thoſe irregular orders. But it is the rule of Chriſt, that maketh a Chriſtian: and therefore we muſt either hold our ſelues ſatisfied with it; or els ſhewe that S. S. Francis, Dominicke and other ſuch like patrons of theirs, haue found out ſomwhat that is more holy &amp; perfect, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which was delivered and eſtabliſhed by Chriſt: which once to thinke or ſpeake were horrible blaſphemie. Verely as no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> will take him to be a right Engliſh-ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> borne, who refuſeth to liue after the lawes, ſtatutes &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: ſo is not he to be deemed a true Chriſtian, who to chooſe embraceth the heſts of men before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Chriſt. Our ſavior himſelfe is plaine &amp; pere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tory in this behalfe:<note place="margin">Mat. 15.9</note> 
               <hi>in vain do me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> worſhip me, teaching doctrins that ar but the traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 13.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; eury pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which my heve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:6602:10"/>
               <hi>hath not planted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>ſhal be rooted vp.</hi> S. Paul ſharpely rebuketh thoſe which ſaid I hold <hi>of Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3.3.</note> 
               <hi>I of Apollos, I of Cephas:</hi> and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the Corinthians as <hi>carnall:</hi> for that by thoſe names they were ſevered &amp; ſundred as it were into ſo many ſortes &amp; ſects of profeſſions. But we (alas) at this daie are growne to ſuch madnes, that we magnifie &amp; extoll the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones: we applaud &amp; admire, yea and adore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the onely perfect men of the world, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining and deſpiſing the name of Chriſtians, made vnto vs expreſly lawfull and honourable by the worde of God, doe call themſelues Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcans, Dominicans, Bernardines, Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctines, Auguſtines and I cannot tell what, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Chriſtians. But howſoever they vaunt themſelues of their perfection,<note place="margin">Miles glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vioſus.</note> like the glorious ſouldier in the comedye of his i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginarie valour, and ſwell like Eſops toade, till they burſt againe with the proude titles of Angelical, Seraphicall, and Cherubinical: yet by the verdit of S. Iohn, or rather of the holy Ghoſt, in deſpight of all Monkiſh Friers and Frierly Monkes, they onely are indeede, and are to be accounted true Chriſtians, which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie themſelues wholy to the obſerving &amp; kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Chriſts commandements.</p>
            <p>But ſome man may aſke what thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which import vs ſo greatly to be kept,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6602:10"/>are? for if he harken to the prelates of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church and popiſh religion they will tel him, they are none other, but the ſame which they both practiſe themſelues, &amp; preſcribe vnto others to be done. But to be reſolved aright of this doubt, he muſt in no wiſe be carried away with ours or theirs, yea or nay: but holde him ſelfe ſure to the word of Chriſt, ſounding in the ſcriptures. For Chriſt Ieſus, as S. Paul bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth record, <hi>being yeſter day, and to day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and the ſame for ever:</hi> it is a cleare caſe, that all ſuch thinges, as Chriſt hath appointed hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be kept, doe &amp; ſhall remaine in ful force, even to the worlds end. And ſeeing he is <hi>the wiſedome of God the father:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.24.</note> and the father gaue the ſpirite vnto him <hi>not by meaſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.34.</note> but in ſuch abundance, as we all partake grace of his fulneſſe: can the perfection of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts be doubted-off, but the perfection of God himſelfe, &amp; of the holy ghoſt, muſt needs bee called into queſtion therwithall? further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in that God, in the old Teſtament, gaue ſuch a law, as might <hi>neither be added-to,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>nor taken-from,</hi> without attaint of high treaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Higheſt, as the holy Ghoſt in ſundry places affirmeth: is it likely, I appeale and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port me to your own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, that our eſtate vnder the Goſpell, in the time of reformation, ſhould be in worſe caſe then theirs, &amp; ſo vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6602:11"/>that it ſhould neede every day, new addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be ſupplied, new peeces of traditions to be patched, to be cobled &amp; clowted thervnto Beſides it is apparent, that Chriſt gaue not ſo much liberty, no not to his Apoſtles, to obtrude and thruſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church, whatſoever ſeemed good vnto them: but he reſtrained their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion with this limitation: <hi>goe gather me diſciples out of all nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 28.19.</note> 
               <hi>teching them to obſerue whatſoever I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">20.</note> Wher vpon S. Paul grew ſo preciſe, that he doubted not, to denounce <hi>anathema</hi> againſt him whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,<note place="margin">Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.</note> though in degree of an <hi>Angell,</hi> that ſhould preſume, to a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nounce any other Goſpel, then what himſelfe, &amp; his fellow Apoſtles had preached and publiſhed before. But it ſhall bee needefull. I ſpeake ſomething of theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, which be they. For though they bee almoſt infinite, being ſeverallye conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in themſelues: yet for plaineneſſe and ſhorteneſſe ſake, they may be all raunged, and as it were marſhalled into three generall rankes.</p>
            <p>The firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendeth all ſuch, as concerne our faith. Amongſt which, that leades the ring, whereby wee are bounde, to beleeue in God alone, according as is put downe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the Decalogge,<note place="margin">Iet. 17.5.</note> or ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: <hi>For curſed be the man that truſteth in man,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6602:11"/>and maketh fleſh his arme.</hi> Next this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that which pointeth-out Chriſt: in affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of whoſe merites and interceſſion, wee may boldely repoſe our truſt and confidence in GOD. For except a man bringe Chriſt with him, to bee his ſpoakeſ-man, in vaine is hee ſent vnto GOD, to treate for mercye: whilſt the teſtimonye of his owne conſcience will accuſe and convict him, to be both a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner &amp; the child of wrath. And that we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt, he himſelf doth vs to wit, wher he ſaith: <hi>this is the wil of God that ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>that evere one which ſeeth the ſon &amp; beleveth in him ſhould haue life everlaſting.</hi> Alſo where he inviteth thoſe that be <hi>weary &amp; loaden</hi> to come vnto him to be diſburdned &amp; refreſhed:<note place="margin">Math. 11.28.</note> &amp; the <hi>thirſty,</hi> to repaire vnto him, &amp; <hi>drinko.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 7.37.</note> But becauſe faith is no vaine opinion, conceaved by the perſwaſion of man, but a ſolid &amp; ſounde apprehenſion of the things, which are exhibited in Chriſt: it ſhall not be amiſſe, if wee conſider a little, what the ſcripture doth report as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt. For vnleſſe we doe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, to be ſuch a one, as hee is there pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed and depainted to be, wee can never ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the commandementes of faith, but ſhall runne headlonge, againſt the perilous rockes of miſ-beleefe, to the everlaſtinge hazard and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6602:12"/>ſhipwracke of our ſouls. For to forge any thing of Chriſt that he is not, is as horrible, as to ſaie there is no Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer therefore is regiſtred in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt, either it toucheth his perſon or his office.</p>
            <p>The perſon of Chriſt is one: &amp; therfore in no wiſe to be devided. Wherein are ioiued two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct natures: the one of the ſelfe-ſame eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, maieſtie &amp; ſubſtance with God the Father; the other in the time prefixed, taken of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marie. Both theſe I ſay, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyned in one perſon, but not confounded. For the Deity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth whole, &amp; is not ſtained with any ſpot of humane infirmity: neither is the humanitie ſwallowed-vp with the glory of the divine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty. But as he is perfect God: ſo is he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe perfect man, conſiſting of a true humane body &amp; reaſonable ſoule. This may be avoued by many manifeſt teſtimonies of holy writte. For the olde Prophets in regarde of the divine nature of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eſai. 7.6.</note> call him <hi>wonderfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Father,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23.6.</note> 
               <hi>coequall with God, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> yea and which more is, the <hi>Lord and God himſelfe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 11.1.53.2.</note> but having reſpect to his manhoode, they name him <hi>a branch, a graffe of the roote of Ieſſe, David, the ſonne of David,</hi> the laſt and <hi>leaſt</hi> amongſt men.<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.1.</note> In the goſpel likewiſe, there is expreſſe mention made of the Godhead
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6602:12"/>of Chriſt; <hi>in the beginning was the worde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> 
               <hi>and the worde was with God, and that word was God:</hi> but the ſame Changeliſt in the ſame place intimating his humane nature ſaith further;<note place="margin">10 30.</note> 
               <hi>and that woorde was made fleſh:</hi> not by making exchaunge of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, but by taking our humanitye into him: For by way of expoſition hee addeth; <hi>and dwelt amonge vs.</hi> So CHRIST himſelfe,<note place="margin">8.58.</note> ſpeaking in the perſon of the ſonne of GOD, ſayeth; <hi>I and the father are one:</hi>
               <note place="margin">14.28.</note> 
               <hi>and before Abraham was, I am:</hi> but in the perſon of man hee ſayeth; <hi>the Father is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then I.</hi> Much might heere bee alleadged for further proofe of this pointe, if neede re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. But let it ſuffice vs, that it is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall commaundemente of CHRIST, neceſſary to bee beleeued of every true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man, that Jeſus Chriſt, in one perſon, is very GOD, and very man:<note n="*" place="margin">This fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of ſpeech, is called of ſome, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcene, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: but commonly, <hi>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio idioma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:</hi> a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of properties: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>as that is vouched of one, which is proper to another.</note> both thoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures being in ſuch ſorte vnited and knit togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the properties of either, doe abide ſound, though by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hypoſtaticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction and vnion betwixte them, it commeth oft to paſſe, that that is attributed vnto whole Chriſt, which properly belongeth but to one of the natures only. Which caution, if we giue not good heede vnto, in reading holy ſcripture, we may ſoone run contrarie, ere we be aware,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6602:13"/>with Arrius, Evion, Marcion, Valentinus, Neſtorius and others, who, through ouerſight in that point, intangled themſelues with many groſſe hereſies, to the great annoyance of the Church, and their owne vtter deſtruction. The informatto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this doctrine is very behoofeful, for the corroborating and ſtrengthning of our weake faith. For ſo much as otherwiſe, Chriſt could not haue atchieued that wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful exploit of our redemption, had he not bin, both God &amp; man. Man; to make ſatiſfaction for man, that had offended: God; to ouercome death, the due ſtipend of ſin, whom no meere man, of him ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was able to ſurpriſe.</p>
            <p>The office of Chriſt, is implied in his names. For if that ſaying of the Poet be found daily verified in a number: <hi>conveniunt fatis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina ſaepe ſuis:</hi> mens names oft proue ſutable &amp; correſpondent to their fortune and deſtinie: the ſame ought eſpecially to take place, in the ſon of God, ſo long longed &amp; looked-for. The name (Jeſus) is an Hebrew word,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and expreſſeth his office, in a more general ſignification, for it ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth as much,<note place="margin">Mat. 1.21.</note> as <hi>a Saviour,</hi> according to the true etymologie thereof, giuen by the Angell. Chriſt, is a Greeke word, and doth more ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally notifie his maner of ſauing vs. For whom the Grecians terme Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the Hebrewes call Meſſias, and is as much in Latine, as <hi>vuctus,</hi> in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6602:13"/>Engliſh, annointed. Now of old, by the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and appointment of God,<note place="margin">1. King 1.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſtes</hi> were wont to be <hi>annointed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 30.30.</note> whom to haue bin types and ſhadowes of Chriſt, then to come, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be gaineſayed: and ſo anſwerably vnto that figure, was our ſauiour called <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is, <hi>annointed.</hi> Not that he was annointed with materiall oile, but as it is in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.7.</note> with the <hi>oile of gladnes:</hi> that is, with the giftes and graces of Gods holy ſpirit, aboue all other his brethren, the ſonnes of men: being conſecrate thereby, to take vpon him the office, both of the chiefe and eternal prieſt-hood, and prince-hood of Gods people. In witnes and token whereof, John Baptiſt ſaw the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 3.1.</note> in a viſible forme <hi>deſcending and lighting on him.</hi> In beleeuing then, and profeſſing the ſon of God, to be Chriſt, we acknowledge and confeſſe him, to be both king and prieſt of Gods people, that is to ſay, of the whole Church. And therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept wee will make of him an image without life, we muſt agniſe in him accordingly the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, aſwell of the one, as of the other. The prieſts office in time paſt, was to teach the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to inſtruct them in the lawe of God, as alſo to pray, and offer ſacrifice for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Theſe things, are al fully performed by Chriſt in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part, for hee did not only teach the people, when he was converſant vpon earth; but ſtill
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6602:14"/>doth to this day, whilſt hee revealeth and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his wil known to the Church by his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and by his ſpirite quickeneth the ſame in the heartes of men. Nay Chriſt is to bee hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, for the only and ſingular doctour and ſchoole-maſter of the Church.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.7.</note> For miniſters doe but execute the externall function onlye, which though it be done, neuer ſo exquiſitely, neuer ſo in printe, as they ſay: yet if Gods ſpirite, doe not inwardely concurre therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, it availeth no more, then if a candle bee ſet before a blinde man, though neuer ſo bright, or a tale tolde to a deafe man, though neuer ſo lowde and ſhrill.<note place="margin">J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epiſt. Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. tract. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> As Saint Auſtine ſaieth very well: thinke not that one man learneth any thing of another: wee may warne by the ſounde of our voyce, but if hee, who teacheth the hearte, bee not within, vaine is the noiſe made without. Neither did hee onlie pray for his, whilſt hee liued in the fleſh, but euen now appeareth before the face of the Father, to play the advocate and interceſſour for vs: hauing offered a ſacrifice, not ſuch a one, as was accuſtomed in the old law, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> himſelfe, his owne body and bloode, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlaughtered on the altar of the croſſe, hath not only taken away the guilte of ſinne, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie due vnto the ſame, but alſo purchaſed the fauour of his Father towardes vs. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6602:14"/>the manner of CHRISTS prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, and theirs in the olde Teſtamente, is ſomewhat different. For the Leviticall prieſts, being but mortall men, ſubiect to death, they needed newe ſucceſſours, to bee ſubſtituted in their roomes, euer as they deceaſed: but CHRIST, in that hee is immortall, and death hath nowe no more ſtroake over him, hee wanteth no ſucceſſour, as no Vicar neither, as who is both able and willing enough of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, to diſcharge that function, which was aſſigned and allotted vnto him of the Father; For vnto him it was ſaide:<note place="margin">Pſal. 110.4</note> 
               <hi>thou art a prieſt for euer, after the order of Melchiſedec.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.17.10.4.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in that the bloode of Oxen and Goates, was not of value ſufficient, to ranſome the ſins of the whole world: &amp; al thoſe ſwarmes of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, vſed in ancient time, were nothing but fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures of that graund-ſacrifice, to be offered on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe; they were oft to be renued:<note place="margin">9.25.</note> But Chriſt once offered, entred not into y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy places made with ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, but into very heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there to appear in the ſight of God for vs: not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhould offer himſelfe often, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one oblation once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, hath obtained for our ſins, plenary deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, full and compleate redemption. Who ſo then wil keepe the commandements of Chriſt, appertaining vnto faith, he muſt conſtantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, that Ieſus Chriſt, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only true, chiefe &amp;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6602:15"/>euerlaſting prieſt of Gods Church: who onlie hath the wordes of eternall life: who only ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth interceſſion for vs to the father: who by the only ſacrifice of his body &amp; blood, once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, &amp; neuer to be reiterated or repeated again, hath pur ged the ſins of the whole world. Now a word or two of his kingdome.</p>
            <p>The duty of a king ſtandeth chiefely, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the people committed to his charge, in ſafety &amp; publique peace. For better performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce whereof, hee muſt make good Lawes, &amp; cauſe them to be put in execution: he muſt be vigilant and watchfull for their well-fare: cheriſh the good: chaſtiſe malefactours: miniſter true iuſtice: ſee euerie man haue his owne: yea and if neede bee, ſhielde and defende his ſubiectes by force of Armes againſt all vniuſt violence and tyrannicall vſurpation. But in Chriſt not one of all thoſe qualities, is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, if wee conſider what the Scripture gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth-out of him. For he ſought the good and tranquillitie of his people ſo earneſtly, that hee thoughte not his owne precious hearte-bloode too deare, to ſpende it, for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theraunce and procuremente thereof. Hee made lawes not onelie availeable for this life, but for the life to come: the ſame hee vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth maugre all aduerſarie power, heaping benefites and bleſſinges vppon ſuch as obey,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6602:15"/>but plagues and puniſhmentes vppon tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours diuerſe and ſundry waies. Neither lacketh hee weapons, where with to eſtabliſh his owne kingdome, and to ſubdue his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Heretofore hee diſcomfited Sathan, the captaine general of al impiety and wickednes: puld-out the ſting of ſinne, that it can no more mortallie wounde vs: vanquiſhed the graue: daunted the power of death: queld and cruſht in pieces the gates of hell. And ſtill hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters daily by his woorde, againſt Anti-Chriſt and all his imps and adherentes, the tyrauntes and wicked ones of this worlde: them hee killeth with the breath of his mouth; yea and many times bringeth moſt horrible iudgementes vppon them: whileſt ſtripping them naked out of all their authority, pompe, riches, honoures and poſſeſſions; hee cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth them with miſerie, contempt and ſhame: whileſt ſcattering their counſelles; defeating their purpoſes; fruſtrating and diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting all their plottes and practiſes; hee tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleth them in the ſnares they had layed to entrappe others with all: and like an arrowe ſhotte againſt a braſen wall, reboundeth their miſchieuous imaginations backe againe vpon their owne heades. Examples heereof are rife, &amp; every where to be ſeene. For what one king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome can there inſtance be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-off, what one,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6602:16"/>in al the world, whoſe laws, priviledges, ſwaie, maieſtie &amp; dominto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue indured ſo many ages, as wee ſee the kingdome and Church of Chriſt hath ſtood &amp; floriſhed inviolably? The famous Monarchie of Aſſiria, which was founded by the firſt tyrantes of the worlde, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier of the Grecians and Perſians, (at whoſe beck whilome the whole world ſtowped, at whoſe frowne they trembled and quaked) what trowe yee nowe, is become of them? are they not cleane ſubverted? are not the very foundations of them vtterly razed, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned topſie turvie, vp-ſide downe? &amp; what an ecclips, hath befalled vnto Rome for all the inſolent crackes, which haue bin made of her, halfe an eye may ſee. To ſay nothing of other puiſſant kingdomes, which ſometime ſhone in exceeding glory, but now quite extinct &amp; ſcarce remembred. Only the kingdome, and Church of Chriſt continueth ſafe and ſounde, &amp; though it hath bene maligned &amp; aſſaulted ſore from time to time, by mighty &amp; malicious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, yet hath it ever bene ſo protected &amp; garded by Chriſt at al aſſaies, that it never miſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>carried: but the more fierce and fierye, the more furious and outragious the enemye was bent againſt it, the more it ſtill abounded in ſtrength and glorye. In which reſpect the ſtate thereof was verye ſignificantlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6602:16"/>vnto Abraham in Geneſis,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.17</note> by a <hi>fire-brande flaming in the middeſt of a ſmoking furnace:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.2.</note> and in Exodus by the <hi>buſh</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſawe <hi>burninge but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed not away.</hi> And for the ſame reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance hath bene likened, ſometimes to Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>momile, which the more it is preſſed-downe and trampled-on, the faſter it groweth, and ſpreadeth farther, and ſmelleth ſweeter: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the palme tree, which the more it is loaden, the more it mounteth vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then: ſometime to a vine,<note place="margin">Juſt. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> de verit. Chriſt religi<hi rend="sup">•</hi> onis tom. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
                  </hi> pag. <hi>224.</hi> lin<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
                  <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> which the more it is cutte, dreſt and pruned, the more fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full it waxeth: ſometimes to roſes and lilies which ſprout and floriſh even amonge ſharpe thornes. So true an oracle is that, not of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo of Delphos, but of the holye Ghoſt: that the <hi>gates of Hell canne never prevaile againſt</hi> the Kingdome <hi>and Church of Chriſt.</hi> And this accounte muſt wee make of Chriſt, if wee will beleeue in him, accordinge to his commaundementes. Wherevnto muſt bee referred whatſoever the ſcripture delivereth of him, and teacheth him to be the whole and ſole ſaviour of the worlde. So that they doe violate and breake the chiefe commandement of Chriſt, who beleeue otherwiſe either of his perſon, or of his office, then he hath diſcloſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6602:17"/>and taught in his worde. They likewiſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, that profeſſe they carry ſuch an opinion of Chriſt in thoſe reſpects, as the trueth requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: but not contenting themſelues with him alone, doe aſcribe part of their ſalvation to their owne workes, or other creatures, as if he without them, were inſufficient to worke the feate. For as there is but <hi>one God,</hi> who will be worſhiped by him ſelfe alone<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo is there but <hi>one mediatour betweene God and man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> our true Immanuel, who is ſo <hi>ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 42.8.</note> that he cannot brooke, that any other perſon, or thing whatſoever, ſhould be ioyned patent with him in the ſame. And thus much of the firſt ranke, or band of Chriſts commandements.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ranke is of thoſe, which belong to the ſervice of God, or externall religion. For albeit the true ſervice of God be ſpirituall and ſtandeth principally in the Canons &amp; rules of faith before ſpecified: yet God like a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful father, tendring the infirmity of vs his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, aloweth certaine outward rites, for the better exerciſing of our inward religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; faith. And therein he hath ſet vs boundes &amp; limites, which wee may not paſſe; leaſt following the current, the tide &amp; ſtreame of our owne wiſedome, we ſhould deviſe any kinde of worſhippe in the ſerving of him, which though it ſeeme
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6602:17"/>never ſo devout and holy in our owne eies (as we are give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> over-much to be enamoured with our owne inventions and good intentions,<note place="margin">Eſt qui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſibi Suffenus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Catul Cacus amor ſui: Horat. Ovid. Met. lib. <hi>3</hi> fab. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Naz.</note> as Narciſſus fel in loue with his owne ſhadowe:) yet can it not ſtand with the nature &amp; glory of God. The Iewes, they had many many cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies preſcribed them, &amp; well: for the more diverſely the promiſed Meſſias, was decyfered and figured out vnto them, the better it was for them, both to kindle their devotion, and to confirme their faith. But nowe ſince the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it ſelfe, is come in place, which was the end of the lawe, all thoſe heapes of ceremonies are vaniſhed, and of right abrogated &amp; aboliſhed: and all thinges, whereby, either our faith is to be holpen, or our devotion to be furthered, doe conſiſt in a fewe chiefe pointes. Amongſt which we may afforde Church aſſemblies, the firſt roome, vy vertue of Chriſts promiſe:<note place="margin">Mat. 18.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>where two or three be gathered togither in my na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e there am I in the midſt of them.</hi> But it ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not, howe oft we flocke &amp; flowe togither, except the thinges be donne, when we meete, for which we ought to aſſemble togither in the name of Chriſt (for otherwiſe goates vſe to hearde togither as well as ſheepe.) Here then commeth, in the miniſterie of the worde, which Chriſt would haue, both ſincerely preached, &amp; attentiuely heard with faith: inſomuch that he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6602:18"/>maketh the hearinge of the woorde, aſpeciall badge and cogniſance,<note place="margin">Joh. 8.47.</note> to knowe his ſervants by,<note place="margin">Luc. 10.42.</note> and highly commendeth <hi>Marye</hi> for that whiles <hi>Martha cumbred her ſelfe aboute much ſerving: ſhe ſate at Ieſus feete &amp; hard him preach.</hi> To this ſtudy of the worde, wee muſt ioyne fervent and heartye prayer: For the heavenly wiſedome is given to none but ſuch,<note place="margin">Jac. 1.5.</note> as ſeeke &amp; ſue for the ſame at the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the father of lights by faithful praier. We muſt make our petitions then vnto God, &amp; not vnto creatures, and that in a liuely faith, which ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth all miſdoubte of Gods good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, &amp; aſſureth vs of his preſence. Theſe praiers, whether they be private or publique, how ſweete a ſavour, howe fragrant a ſmell they yeelde in the noſe-thrilles of the Lord, wee may eſteeme by his vehemente and often callinge on vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.14.</note> to vſe them: proteſting, hee ſetteth more by the invocation of his name, then by all other externall ſervice what ſoever. And for our better direction in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, wee muſt learne, as to ſubiect &amp; ſubmit our ſelues in all things, to the wil &amp; pleaſure of God: ſo to craue to be heard in all that we aſke only in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mediatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Jeſus Chriſt. For being of our ſelues by nature corrupt and ſinners, wee are not in caſe, to preſcribe vnto God, what he ſhould do for vs; no nor without
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6602:18"/>our mediator Chriſt Jeſus, ſo much as to dare to preſent or proſtrate our ſelues before the throne of his divine maieſty: as Chriſt himſelf giveth to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, informing vs,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.23.</note> both to pray <hi>in his name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6.10.</note> &amp; in our praiers to ſay <hi>thy will be don in earth, as it is in heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> Theſe things at atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded and waited-on, with the right vſe &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to wit, Baptiſme &amp; the Lords ſupper, where we muſt be wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full circuſiſpecte, that they be neither profaned through irreverence or contempt, nor polluted with ſuperſtition: remembringe, howe care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Saint Paul was to reforme ſuch abuſes,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.23</note> as had crept into them amonge the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, according to the preciſe patterne of Chriſtes originall inſtitution, not daring for his life to ſwarue one heares breadth from it. Theſe, theſe bee the pointes, wherein the outwarde ſervice of God, doth in a manner conſiſt: <hi>viz.</hi> holye and Chriſtian aſſemblies, the preaching of the woord, prayers and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes. All which as they were at firſt ſimply ordayned by CHRIST: ſo were they duetifully receaved, and faithfullye ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of the primatiue Church, without alteration or depravation. They that dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addict &amp; giue themſelues vnto theſe things, bee they, that followe the <hi>commandementes</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and by their ſo dooinge evidentlye
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6602:19"/>declare, that they haue the true knoweledge and faith of Chriſt in them. But ſuch as ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them aſide, broach newe ceremonies of their owne brueing; abandon the Church; 01 contemne the worde of God; embrace the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of men; direct their prayers vnto creatures, or in them vſe the mediation of others to the father beſides Chriſt: pervert the right vſe of the Sacraments; and to all theſe adde images, aulters, newe conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; yea and coyne newe Sacraments too: theſe cannot iuſtly be ſaide, to keepe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes of Chriſte, in aſmuch as the thinges which they vſe, were never authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſt: being indeede but birdes, as the ſaying is, of their owne hatching, fancies of their owne deviſing, without ground and warrant of the worde, the onely authenticall rule of our religion, and infallible pole-ſtarre for our direcion, in the ſervice of God.</p>
            <p>The thirde ranke of Chriſtes commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes compriſeth all thoſe, which ſerue for managing of our behaviour &amp; manners. Theſe may be extended as farre, as our whole life, and every action thereof doth ſtreach: but Saint John in the thirde chapter follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, reduceth them all vnto three gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall heades, where hee attributeth to the children of God, purification, righteouſnes,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6602:19"/>and brotherly loue or charity. Wee are purged indeede, by the bloode of Chriſt, yet ſo, that wee neede daiely, <hi>to waſh our feete,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.10.</note> to ſhake-of the vncleane affections of the fleſh which carrie vs captiue into the triumph of ſinne. For as dirt and balme cannot well bee tempered together: ſo no more can wee haue fellowſhippe and communion with God,<note place="margin">Lev. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who is holineſſe it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Eſai.33.19.</note> ſo long as wee lye drowned in the dregges of our owne naturall corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, never once waving ſo much as a hande or a foote to get out. Righteouſnes includeth both tables: when as wee yeelde both to God, and our neighbour, whatſoever is due vnto ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, by the lawe. Charitie doth not only prohibit iniuries &amp; wrongs: but alſo inioyneth the doing of good. But theſe points, becauſe they be daiely beaten-on in your hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: let it ſuffice at this time, that I haue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pointed-at them. Holding for moſt certaine, as a caſe overruled vnto vs by the holy ghoſt, that they are but hers, diſſemblers, and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, as many as doe not imploie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, to the obſerving and <hi>keeping of Gods comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts:</hi> how glorious a ſhewe ſoever otherwiſe they make of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>knowledg</hi> of Chriſt &amp; his profeſſion. But I ſee, I haue ſtaied over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in handling this former part: I wil ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as it were vpon the ſpurre poſſe over the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:6602:20"/>other ſo much the more ſpeedily.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>5. <hi>But hee that keepeth his worde, in him is the love of God perfect indeede: Hereby we know that we are in him.</hi>
               </hi>
            </q>
            <p>This is the firſt reaſon, whereby our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt and Apoſtle goeth about to iuſtifie the foreſaide Propoſition, being taken (as I tolde you) of the effects, towit, the loue of God, which the knowledg of Chriſt ingendreth in vs, and may be framed in forme of argument, on this faſhion:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hee that loveth God truly, knoweth God truely:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But hee that keepeth Chriſts commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, loveth God truely:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ergo, <hi>hee that keepeth Chriſts commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, knoweth God truely, and is a true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an indeede.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Which conſequence to be ſoundly inferred, not only ſcripture, but even common ſence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth. For is it poſſible a man ſhoulde loue God, whome he knoweth not? the Poet could ſing,<note place="margin">Ovid.</note> 
               <hi>ignoti nulla cupido:</hi> vncooth; vnkiſt: that which is vnknowne, is commonly vnregarded and out of requeſt, be it of never ſo great excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in it ſelfe. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: loue doth breede of the ſight and knowledge of a thing. If Eſops cocke had knowne the worth of the precious ſtone, he woulde not haue ſet ſo light
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6602:20"/>by it: but becauſe hee knewe not the value, therefore he eſteemed more of a barely corne. Nowe hee that is ignoraunt of Chriſt, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer knowe God.<note place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> For hee is the <hi>brightneſſe of his glorie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>and the ingraued forme of his perſon:</hi> and <hi>no man hath ſeene GOD at anytime, but the ſonne, which is in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the father hee hath declared him.</hi> So that a full knowledge of Ieſus Chriſt muſt of neceſſity goe before, eſpecially ſeeing a colde profeſſion of the loue of GOD is not enough, but wee ſtande bounde to loue him aboue all thinges, to relie wholy vppon him, and for his ſake, to relinquiſh father,<note place="margin">Math. 10 3.7.16.24.</note> mother, wife, children, yea and our ſelues and all.<note place="margin">Marc. 8.34.</note> But againe this ſo greate loue of GOD, cannot bee without the keeping of Chriſtes commaundementes: it being the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and propertie of loue, to faſhion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it ſelfe, as neare as poſſible may bee, vnto the will and diſpoſition of the party, whome it affecteth. So the ſonne is carefull to obey his fathers commaundementes not driuen of anie ſeruile or ſlauiſh feare: but moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of a filiall and childe-like loue hee bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth towarde him. And God, for none other cauſe, requireth vs to loue him, with all our heartes, with all our ſtrength, and with all out ſoules: but that that loue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6602:21"/>ſhoulde frame vs, to a dutifull obedience to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him; inſomuch that wee ſhall thinke; nothing too much wee doe, to bee ioyned with him, who is our only felicitie and ſoueraigne good, ſo tenderly and intirely beloued of vs. And therefore, ſith neither the loue of God, canne bee ſeparated from the knowledge of CHRIST, nor it, from an holy life or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred according to the preſcript of his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes: the Apoſtle, yee ſee, hath ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently auerred his purpoſe, that they which <hi>keepe Chriſtes commaundementes, knowe Chriſt</hi> indeede, and are true Chriſtians. As for the perfect loue hee ſpeaketh-of, it is not to bee conſtrued in that ſence, as though wee could in this life, arriue vnto the perfection of loue, or of any other vertue: for (God knowes) as wee knowe but in parte, ſo wee loue but in in parte. But either to recommende vnto vs the continuall indeuour of perfection, which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery true Chriſtian, according to the proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſtrength of grace receiued, ought to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire vnto, and ſtriue towardes, though it be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his reach to attaine vnto it, vntil the world to come,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.28.</note> when God ſhall bee all in all, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly conſummate the good worke, which he hath here graciouſly begunne: or els, the worde perfect muſt be taken, as oppoſite to feined, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an Hebraiſme, very vſuall in diuine ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6602:21"/>ſo that perfect loue betokeneth true,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> perfect, for which <hi>Targhúm</hi> hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but <hi>Hier. ſimplex:</hi> and Lxx. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ideſt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Gel. non fictus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus:</hi> which is, not with out fault, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out double nes or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling. See for all Gen. 25.27.</note> hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſincere and vnfeined loue, which God of his mercy will accept and crowne, though it come many aces ſhorte, of that abſolute degree of perfection, which the rigour of the lawe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely exacteth, meaſuring his giftes in vs (ſuch is the profounde riches of his goodneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs,) not by the effect, but affect of our doings. And the better to excite and ſtir vs vppe heereunto our Apoſtle proceedeth further, and ſheweth, what ſingular fruite, profite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity wee ſhall reape thereby, which beeing duely weighed, is able to ſet an edge on the blu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt apperite, if it haue any mettall of the holy Ghoſt in it. For he ſaith: <hi>Hereby wee knowe that we are in him.</hi> The loue of God the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which begetteth in vs, the keeping of Chriſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, is a ſure ſigne &amp; vndoubted certificate that wee are ingraffed into Chriſt, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt dignity, preeminence and prerogatiue in the worlde, and alone is of efficacy ſufficient to vnderſet and ſtabliſh our weake faith, againſt all the doubtings of fraile fleſh, if there were no other piller, as there be infinite, to ſupporte and proppe it with beſide. For if wee bee in him, hee muſt needes bee in vs, according to that comfortable ſaying of his:<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>if any man loue mee, hee will keepe my worde, and my Father will loue him, and wee will come
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6602:22"/>vnto him and will dwell with him.</hi> So that hee that <hi>knoweth</hi> God truely, <hi>loveth</hi> him truely, &amp; <hi>keepeth his commandements,</hi> hath not only Chriſt, but alſo the father reſtaunt and dwelling in him: which is the aſſured ſalvation of man, and procureth that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, bringeth that bliſſe with it, which al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and bliſſe of this worlde, is not able to mach or counter-vaile, how notable ſoever. Thus the Apoſtle, after the example of Chriſt, conſidering how dull and lumpiſh we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every thing that good is, vſeth moſt forcible motiues, as ſharpe ſpurres, to pricke vs fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and as ſtrong ropes to drawe vs on, to the performance of thoſe thinges, which hee would induce vs vnto. And becauſe it is the caſt of every body, be they never ſo deſtitute of grace, never ſo bereft of Gods holy ſpirite, &amp; vnto every good worke reprobate, to pretend themſelues never the leſſe, to bee of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe, which are incorporate into Chriſt, and have CHRIST abiding in them: therefore to diſcover their maſke, and plucke the viſard of hypocriſie cleane awaie from their faces, hee taketh occaſion thereby to inculcate, to vrge and grate vpon their duety againe, ſaying:</p>
            <q>
               <hi>6. <hi>He that ſaith, he remaineth in him ought even ſo to walke as hee hath walked.</hi>
               </hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:6602:22"/>
            <p>This is the other reaſon, and is like that which he made before in the <hi>1.</hi> chapter, of the light. He that will be ioyned &amp; coupled togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with God, muſt indevour to reſemble him in conditions: but God is light and in him is no darkeneſſe at all: therefore hee that will bee one with God, muſt walke in the lighte of vertue and trueth, and not in the darckeneſſe of ignorance and ſin. By a like reaſon he teacheth here, that ſuch as will be Chriſtians, muſt imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the example of Chriſt &amp; tread in his ſteps. But the argument carries the more force with it, by reaſon of the ſtreight coniunction, wherin we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bined with Chriſt. For it is the work of faith, that we are graſſed into Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue againe from him of his ſpirite: by meane whereof, it commeth to paſſe, that in all our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, there appeareth a liuely picture of the life of Chriſt. Which vnion Sainte Paule hauing an eie vnto, ſaith: <hi>thus I liue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>yet not I now, but Chriſt liueth in mee.</hi> But how can they <hi>walke</hi> otherwiſe then Chriſt hath <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked</hi> in whome Chriſt by his ſpirite liveth? For the ſpirite of Chriſt is neuer <hi>idle:</hi> but where it is, there it doeth regenerate, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the luſtes of the fleſh, and reſiſt ſinne. Nowe the manner of CHRISTS <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</hi> and what kinde of life he lead on earth, is faithfully deſcribed by the Evangeliſtes in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6602:23"/>Goſpell, whatſoever therfore wee finde inrow led there of him, it behooveth vs, if we will not glory of his name in vaine, to tranſporte the ſame by imitation into our liues and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Surely ſynce Chriſtians borrow their name of Chriſt, it is meete, requiſite and our bounden duty, that wee ſhoulde be, as diligent in learning his doctrine, that wee may knowe what to profeſſe: ſo carefull in obſerving his dooings, that wee may adorne and bewtyfie our profeſſion with Godly demeanour. It is a ſhame for any man, to profeſſe himſelfe, to be a ſcrivener, if he cannot vſe his penne; or a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not handle his weapon: none can wel claime the title without the effects. None can well take the name of a preacher, except he bee able by the word of God to teach, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>vince, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, inſtruct; nor of a Carpenter except he can hewe, and ſquare, and plaine, and frame and foyne the timber together: ſo cannot yee bee Chriſtians, except yee bring-forth the workes of Chriſtians. A Chriſtian, is no mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call fantaſie, but an eſſentiall thinge. It is a name of equity, of iuſtice, of trueth, mercy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, chaſtity, wiſedome, patience, humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, devotion: neither can ye of right chalenge the name, if yee bee voide of the workes. He is a Chriſtian, that ſuteth himſelfe in all pointes vnto the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt. We read in Mathew
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:6602:23"/>of S. Peter, that <hi>as hee ſate in the Hall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27.69</note> 
               <hi>a maide came to him ſayinge, thou alſo waſt with Ieſus of Galile.</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 71.</note> 
               <hi>And when hee went out into the porch, another maide ſawe him and ſaide vnto them that were there, This man was with Ieſus of Nazareth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſ. 73.</note> 
               <hi>After a while came vnto him, they that ſtoode-by. and ſaide vnto Peter, ſurelye thou art alſo one of them: for even thy ſpeech bewraieth thee.</hi> Even ſo, my brethren, in like ſort ſhould bee our manners and carriage, our words and our deedes and all our actions of life, in loue in ioy, in peace, long-ſuffring, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, meekeneſſe, temperance, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good-works and fruites of the holy ghoſt, that all that ſee vs, may bee inforced ſtreight to ſay of vs, that wee bee Chriſtians, havinge our whole life in all partes, and every linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, ſo far forth as the frailty of our humane eſtate and condition will permit, ſqua red by the patterne of Chriſts example. Such in olde time was the life of all, that marched vnder Chriſts banner. Iohn Baptiſt was a <hi>burning and a ſhininge candle:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.35.</note> S. Paul an <hi>example</hi> of integrity:<note place="margin">Act. 9.36.</note> Dorcas <hi>full of good workes and almes deedes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.15.</note> The Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <hi>ſhone as lightes in the worlde,</hi> their liues did teſtifie what they were. Iuſtine Martyr witneſſeth of himſelfe, that hee was firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6602:24"/>to the faith of Chriſt, for the liking that bee had of the innocente and godly life of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men. But if all that this day profeſſe the name of CHRIST, were weyed in this ballance, were examined and tryed by this touch-ſtone, alas, alas, howe many of vs woulde bee founde too light? How few would prooue currant Chriſtians? What one is there amongeſt an hundreth, that ſetteth himſelfe, to followe the preſident of Chriſts example, to walke in his ſteppes, to liue his life? nay whome hath not Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, brought to his bent, trained to his lure, wryed to his crooked by as? It is recorded of a running Muſition that ſetting his ſchollers to a rude minſtrill to learne muſique of him,<note place="margin">Biſhoppe Iuell.</note> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they went, he gaue them this caveat by the way, whatſoever ye ſee your maſter doe before you, ſee that yee avoide it, and doe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; hee is but a bungler and his leſſons and manner of fingring naught. To vſe a like compariſon betweene vnlike perſons: wee come to ſchoole to Chriſt, to learne of him, how wee ought to liue; but wheras we ſhould followe him in all thinges, hee being the onely expreſſe ſamplar and rule of all Godlineſſe, it ſeemeth by the whole trade and courſe of our life, that wee deale by him, as the Muſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hade his ſchollers doe by the bad minſtrell
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6602:24"/>For looke whatſoever wee ſee Chriſt hath done before vs, wee goe as nere as wee can, to doe the cleane contrary, as by laying his doings and ours together, will moſt manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Hee was holy; we ſinfull: he heavenly; we earthly he ſpirituall; we carnall: he obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Gods will in all things; we rebellious: he humble; we puft-vp with pride: hee chaſte; we incontinent: he ſober; we intemperant: hee zelous of Gods glory; we keye-cold: he patient; we murmurors: he quiet; wee quarelous: hee meeke; we ſurly: he a peace-maker; we ſowers of debate: he compaſſionate; we ſtrait-lated in one bowels: hee loyall; we trecherous: hee libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; wee covetous: hee mercifull; we cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el. Finally, his life was a mirrour of all true holineſſe and righteouſneſſe: but ours, a ſincke of all carnality, diſſolutenes &amp; Epicuriſme, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning our ſelues for the moſt part, more like brute beaſts, by the motion of our paſſions, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like good Chriſtians, by the line and levell of Chriſts moſt bleſſed exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. But be not decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed: this lip-profeſſion is no armour of proofe againſt the deadlye ſhotte of GODS wrath full indignation. If wee continue thus to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie CHRIST in our liues; whome in tongue and other outwarde appearance, wee ſeeme to profeſſe: to drawe neare vnto GOD with our lippes; our heartes being all
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6602:25"/>togither alienated and eſtraunged from him: to make a face of amity with the Lorde; and practiſe enemitie: to pretende truce in words; and in deedes proclaime open warre and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility againſt him. If wee bee only hearers of the worde; and not doers of the ſame: talkers of the Goſpell: not walkers after the Goſpell: <hi>knowers of Chriſt,</hi> not <hi>keepers of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes:</hi> Let vs hope for no better, but to haue our portion with hypocrites, in the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone: for the mouth of the Lord,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.19.</note> hath ſealed it. Certes we may read our doome in the fig-tree, which for all it was garniſhed with goodly greene leaues: yet becauſe it was vnfruitfull, it was accurſed. The Iewes cried-out <hi>the temple of the Lorde,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 7.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>the temple of the Lorde,</hi> we haue <hi>the temple of the Lorde</hi> amongſt vs: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their life was not conformable to their profeſſion, their ſacrifices became abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto the Lord, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelus, though the peculi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ar people of God, were at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth vtterly diſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for baſtards &amp; caſt-awaies.<note place="margin">Revel 2.5. verſ. 4.</note> The ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dleſtick was remoued out of Epheſus, for leauing their firſt works. Let vs like wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by other folks harmes learne to beware.<note place="margin">Foelix quem faciunt alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na pericula <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tum.</note> Let botemen looke one way, and rowe another: let the crab-fiſhſe forward, and ſwim backward; let ſtage-play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, put-on other perſons, then they are: let that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6602:25"/>profane proverbe, ſaying &amp; doing is two mens offices: be verified among the heathen and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels; let it haue no place among vs, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Chriſt. Let our converſation and our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, our wordes and our workes, our lipps &amp; our liues, our handes &amp; our hartes, our ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and our doings, agree in one tune, drawe in one line together, as beſeemeth &amp; beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth good Chriſtians: els,<note place="margin">Forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed they ſay.</note> if we bee guilty of the ſame hypocriſie the Iewes were, let vs bee ſure to ſmart for it, as the Iewes did. In a worde, let vs bee the ſame men indeede wee would ſo faine ſeeme to be in ſhew. We would bee called Chriſtians, let vs then walke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of Chriſt: otherwiſe it will not advantage vs, as Origen ſaith, to confeſſe that Chriſt is come in the fleſh, which hee tooke of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary; if in this our fleſh, we diſclaime the ende wherefore he came, which was that wee being deliuered out of the handes of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, mighte ſerue the Lorde in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, all the daies of our liues. We woulde bee called the children of light; if then in place of the workes of the light, we delight &amp; wallow in the workes of darkenes: what other may wee expecte, but to bee caſt out into vtter darknes, with the Devill and his Angels? We would be taken for the Lordes harveſt; if then, for the good corne of vertue and godlines, wee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6602:26"/>yeelde nothing but chaffe of vanity, and cares of wickednes and ſin: what other may bee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked-for, but to be gathered by reapers into bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and to be throwen into everlaſting fire? Wee would be counted for good ground, if the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drinking-in the raine and dewe of Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which ſhower downe ſo oft, &amp; ſo ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vppon vs, we bring not forth good hearbes, but weedes &amp; brambles &amp; briers: we are neare vnto curſing, whoſe end is to be burned. Wee would be eſteemed for a choyce vinyard, which the Lord hath planted in a fertill ſoyle, which he hath fenced, dreſſed &amp; manured, which hee hath watered &amp; cheriſhed with al the ſtreames of his goodnes, if now in ſteed of ſweete grapes of ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctity &amp; good works, we bring-forth bitter cluſters &amp; grapes of gall, of lewdnes &amp; vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life: then is our iudgment moſt ſeverely, but moſt deſervedly awarded alredy: he ſhal break downe the hedge of our vineyears, and laye it waſt, ſo that they that go-by, ſhal make havock of the grapes, &amp; the wild-bore out of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſhall roote it vp. God be mercifull vnto vs and bleſſe vs, &amp; ſhewe vs the light of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, &amp; grant vs grace, ſo to profeſſe his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten, &amp; well belooved ſonne, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: that knowing him, we may loue him, and loving him, in ſuch ſort keepe his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp; followe his example, that in the end,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6602:26"/>we may liue &amp; raigne with him everlaſtingly, in his heavenly kingdome; whervnto he bring vs, who hath ſo dearly purchaſed the ſame for vs, even Ieſus Chriſt, our onely King and high-prieſt to whome with the father and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons and one God, be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred all honour, power, glorye and dominion now and evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
